<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM "./tei/tei_Mazzeo.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="Foglio_XSLT.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <!--File description-->
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!--Title, author and encoding's responsable-->
                <title>Keep Power-Line Pollution Out of Your Computer</title>
                <author xml:id="auth" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q16241078">
                  <persName xml:lang="en">
                    <forename>Steve </forename>
                    <surname>Ciarcia</surname>
                  </persName>
                </author>
                <respStmt xml:id="AM">
                    <resp>Converted to XML encoding by</resp>
                    <persName>
                      <forename>Alessandro </forename>
                      <surname>Mazzeo</surname>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <!--Information about editions-->
            <editionStmt>
                <p>1' edition, Byte Magazine, <date>1983.</date></p>
            </editionStmt>
            <!--Information about paper distribution-->
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>McGraw-Hill</distributor>
                <publisher>Byte Publications</publisher>
                <pubPlace>U.S.A.</pubPlace>
                <pubPlace>Canada</pubPlace>
                <pubPlace>U.K.</pubPlace>
                <date when="1983-12-01">1983-12-01</date>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence>Public Domain</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <!--Information about the source where the article is taken-->
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct type="journal" xml:lang="en">
                    <analytic>
                        <title level="a">Keep Power-Line Pollution Out of Your Computer</title>
                        <author ref="#auth">
                          <persName xml:lang="en">
                            <forename>Steve </forename>
                            <surname>Ciarcia</surname>
                          </persName>
                        </author>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title type="main" level="j">Byte</title>
                        <title type="sub">the small systems journal</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Byte Publications</publisher>
                            <publisher>A McGraw-Hill Publication</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>U.S.A.</pubPlace>
                            <pubPlace>Canada</pubPlace>
                            <pubPlace>U.K.</pubPlace>
                            <date when="1983-12-01">1983-12-01</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">8</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="num">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="44">36-44</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <!--Information about encoding-->
        <encodingDesc>
            <!--Project's purpose-->
            <projectDesc>
                <p>
                    The project was born as an exercise for the exam of text encoding. The choosen text is a stretch from an article of Byte Magazine, 
                    <date when="1983-12-01">December 1983</date>, the text speak about a common matter of computer users, the power-line pollution. 
                    This inconvenience is a interference inside power line that could cause voltage anomalies, the consequence is damage to home computer. 
                    Infact in '80 years this problem was the principal cause of guaste in feeder. 
                    <persName ref="#auth" xml:lang="en"><forename>Steve </forename><surname>Ciarcia</surname></persName> in this article propose his solution.
                </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <!--Declaration about common encoding editing-->
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction status="high">
                    <p>Errors in transcription have been controlled manually, and there were not errors.</p>
                </correction>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Many of end-line hyphenations have been removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>All technical information have been expanded with a gloss, and all abbreviations have been further expanded.</p>
                </interpretation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Measure units and other text elements have been normalized.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="all" placement="internal">
                    <p>All punctuation marks in the source text have been retained.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="all">
                    <p>All quotations in the source text have been retained.</p>
                </quotation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The text has been subdivided in macrosection (eg. advertises-section, addresses-section ecc..) and in microsection identfied by paragraph elements or other elements.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <!--Not bibliographic description: text language and text typology-->
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>Article</term>
                    <term>Tech article</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="EN">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <!--Summary about revision history of this project-->
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2017-12-03" who="#AM">Wrote text introduction</change>
            <change when="2017-12-05" who="#AM">Text encoding</change>
            <change when="2017-12-06" who="#AM">Text encoding correction and adding other elements</change>
            <change when="2017-12-07" who="#AM">Donwload an upgrade of my DTD from TEI ROMA and
                adding images, creating xslt</change>
            <change when="2017-12-08" who="#AM">Started translation in Italian, other
                corrections.</change>
            <change when="2017-12-09" who="#AM">Completed Italian translation but aborted in final
                project, rebuilding xslt.</change>
            <change when="2017-12-10" who="#AM">Complete document revision</change>
            <change when="2018-02-12" who="#AM">Rewriting a new xslt</change>
            <change when="2018-02-23" who="#AM">Text encoding correction</change>
            <change when="2018-03-16" who="#AM">Removing translation section</change>
            <change when="2018-04-06" who="#AM">Corrections on DTD</change>
            <change when="2018-05-17" who="#AM">Encoding new elements</change>
            <change when="2019-03-26" who="#AM">Expanding teiHeader, various corrections</change>
            <change when="2019-03-27" who="#AM">generating new DTD from TEI ROMA, rebuilding xslt</change>
            <change when="2019-03-28" who="#AM">Improoving xslt, css adaption</change>
            <change when="2019-03-29" who="#AM">Adding facsimile</change>
            <change when="2019-03-30" who="#AM">Building xslt</change>  
            <change when="2019-04-01" who="#AM">Improoving xslt</change>
            <change when="2019-04-02" who="#AM">Other corrections in xml</change>
            <change when="2019-04-03" who="#AM">Restyling CSS, correcting js</change>
            <change when="2019-04-04" who="#AM">Generated html output</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--introduction: Contains the title and the text introduction, teorically it could be inserted in front, 
            but with the text on two pages, I've prefered to insert it in a div.-->
            <div type="introduction">
                <pb n="36"/>
                <figure xml:id="IM1">
                    <graphic url="./img/fig1.png"/>
                    <figDesc> Photo 1: Your computers and other electronic equipment are vulnerable
                        to disturbances transmitted through the power line. Most of the components
                        necessary for transient and noise suppression can be purchased from Radio
                        Shack. Shown here are a commercial <choice><abbr>EMI</abbr><expan>Electro Magnetic Interference</expan></choice>/<choice><abbr>RFI</abbr><expan>Radio Frequency Interference</expan></choice> line filter made by Corcom and
                        two <orgName>General Electric</orgName> metal-oxide varistors. </figDesc>
                </figure>
                <head>Keep Power-Line Pollution Out of Your Computer</head>
                <p rend="italic">by <persName ref="#auth" xml:lang="en"><forename>Steve</forename> <surname>Ciarcia</surname></persName></p>
                <cb n="p36_c1"/>
                <p> A visitor once called the <name>Circuit Cellar</name> my
                        <geogFeat>mountaintop</geogFeat> wilderness retreat. Since he lived in the
                    center of <region>Manhattan</region>, the few oak and birch trees around my
                    house seemed to him like a forest, and because he could view scenery further
                    away than a block or two he must have felt like he was on <geogName>Mount
                        Whitney</geogName>. Well, my area is one of the higher points in
                        <country>Connecticut</country>, but that isn't very high. It's barely a
                    prairie-dog mound to someone from <country>Montana</country>. Life in a rural
                    location has its special pleasures. I get to plow the <cb n="p36_c2"/> snow from
                    my own driveway, trim back the ever-encroaching foliage and rake the leaves,
                    pile four cords of wood for the stove each winter (<ref target="#refe1">see reference 1</ref>), fight off
                    the local animal population, and <emph>spend large sums of money repairing damage done
                    to my electronic equipment by electrical disturbances.</emph> This last item is the
                    only one that really annoys me. Every year I can count on experiencing some
                    equipment failure attributable to an external electrical impulse, usually coming
                    in through the power line. </p>
                <p> For <cb n="p36_c3"/> three years, just like clockwork, the first thunderstorm in
                    <date when="--06">June</date> wiped out a <objectName>DECwriter II</objectName> terminal connected to one of my computers. After
                    the first two times of spending a few hours replacing blown chips, I got smart
                    and installed <term ref="#sok" rend="italic">sockets</term>. (Now I even know
                    in advance which chips will be blown.) Last summer I kept the printer
                    unconnected when I wasn't using it. But the elements were not to be denied.
                    During an <date when="--08">August</date> thunderstorm, lightning struck my house. I can't say for sure
                    where the bolt ac <fw type="pageNum"><num rend="bold">36</num> <date when="1983-12">December 1983</date> &#169; Byte Publications Inc.</fw><pb n="37"/>
                    <ptr target="#epgh"/>
                    <cb n="p37_c1"/>tually hit (there were no burn marks or other visible clues),
                    but I suspect the point of entry was the power line. I remember seeing an
                    indistinct flash of light, hearing a tremendous crash, and then standing in
                    darkness. My assistant <persName><forename>Jeanette</forename></persName> saw a bright blue glow
                    behind one of the computers. Such a tremendous power surge is not kind to
                    semiconductor-based equipment. The casualties included one computer, one video
                    camera, two video monitors, a microwave receiver, and probably several other
                    assorted items I haven't found yet. The damage did not include the <objectName>DECwriter</objectName>
                    (safely unplugged since <date when="--05">May</date>), but it was over <measure type="currency">$3000</measure>. In <date when="--12">December</date>, thunderstorms
                    are not an immediate threat, but as I write this in early <date when="--09">September</date> the memory
                    is still fresh and I still have a month of potentially violent weather to
                    contend with. I am forced to consider some defensive measures. Perhaps by
                    relating my experiences I can save you from a similar fate. Of course, lightning
                    isn't the sole cause of electrical disturbances; you don't have to wait for a
                    thunderstorm to be a victim. Many kinds of trouble can be ducted into your
                    computer through the power line. In the <date when="1981-01">January 1981</date>
                    <name>Circuit Cellar</name> article (<ref target="#refe2">reference 2</ref>), I wrote about <term
                        ref="#intfM">electromagnetic interference</term> <choice>
                            <abbr>(EMI)</abbr>
                            <expan>ElectroMagnetic Interference</expan>
                        </choice> and <term ref="#intfR">radio-frequency interference</term> <choice>
                            <abbr>(RFI)</abbr>
                            <expan>Radio-Frequency Interference</expan>
                        </choice> . This month I'd like to pick up the saga by describing
                    other forms of electrical pollution that occur on power lines. Afterward, I'll
                    describe a few simple, inexpensive means of dealing with them. </p>
            </div>
            <!--Contains the relevant section of text, where the author speaks about powerline and its pollution.
            This article is subdivided in virtual section of text where the content is grouped for the same arguments.-->
            <div type="article">
                <!--Summary section 1: It's like a second preface. The author speaks about common issue 
                in powerline and why it could happen.-->
                <div type="sezione" n="1">
                    <head rend="bold">The Power Line: A Hostile Environment</head>
                    <p> The lines leaving your local utility company's generating plant carry
                        electrical power that in most respects is pure, smooth, and constant.</p>
                    <p> However, as the power is routed through the distribution network, it comes
                            <ptr target="#cpy"/><cb n="p37_c2"/> under the increasing aberrant influence of external
                        forces and the connection or shedding of electrical loads. Your
                        susceptibility to these aberrations depends on your location in the
                        distribution system. If you are close to the power plant, you should have
                        relatively few, with the low <term ref="#src-imp">source-impedance</term> of the generator and short
                        distance of the transmission line limiting the influence of external forces.
                        But rural customers at the end of the line usually experience the full
                        effect. While the utilities try to distribute power evenly, the presence of
                        a large-scale user of electrical power along the line between the generator
                        and you can greatly affect the quality and quantity of the power you get. If
                        you own a personal computer, you should be concerned about the quality of
                        the power you feed it. Power-line irregularities cause problems for
                        computers and other digital equipment because certain kinds of extraneous
                        electrical pulses can be interpreted as data or instructions, causing errors
                        in operation. You face hazards every time you plug in a piece of electronic
                        equipment, but there are certain precautionary measures that can protect
                        your computer. The degree of sensitivity depends somewhat on the type of
                        equipment and the type of disturbances. As the operating speed of digital
                        equipment increases, its tolerance to power-line pollution lessens.
                        High-speed processors and memory components are susceptible to fast
                        transients. (Dynamic memories, which must be periodically refreshed, are
                        particularly susceptible.) Disk drives and displays, on the other hand, are
                        more affected by lasting surges and sags in operating voltage. </p>
                </div>
                <!--Summary section 2: The author speaks in details about the phenomenans that cause disturbance in powerline.-->
                <div type="sezione" n="2">
                    <head rend="bold">Common Sources of <emph>Woe</emph></head>
                    <p> Electrical power-line disturbances can come from either natural or manmade
                        sources. Of the many ways the power line can be disturbed, the several
                        varieties of voltage fluctuation <cb n="p37_c3"/> most often cause problems
                        with computer equipment. These fluctuations can be categorized by source and
                        severity, as follows: </p>
                    <list>
                        <label rend="bold"> Blackouts.</label>
                        <item>
                            <p> A blackout is a total power outage&#8212;the voltage goes to zero.
                                Obviously if no alternate source of power is available as a backup,
                                computer equipment will be severely affected, and data will be lost.
                                Blackouts generally affect only a small number of utility customers
                                (fewer than 5 percent) during a year and generally last less than <measure type="time">10
                                seconds</measure>. </p>
                        </item>
                        <label rend="bold">Brownouts.</label>
                        <item>
                            <p> A brownout is typically a corrective action taken by the utility
                                when power demand exceeds generating capacity. The utility reduces
                                the output voltage from a <term ref="#nomV">nominal <measure type="voltage">120 V (volts)</measure>
                                    by 5 to 15 percent</term>. When the voltage is thus reduced, the
                                resistive load presented to the generators by the distribution
                                network consumes less power. Generally speaking, most consumer and
                                industrial equipment designed for use in <bloc>North America</bloc>
                                functions properly when supplied with current within the range from
                                <measure type="voltage">105 to 130 V</measure>. But when operating at either extreme, the equipment is
                                more vulnerable to disruption from some other power-line anomaly.
                                Fortunately, power companies rarely reduce the voltage by more than
                                7 percent. </p>
                        </item>
                        <label rend="bold">Voltage transients.</label>
                        <item>
                            <p> The phenomena of voltage transients include surges of voltage above
                                the specified normal, voltage sags below, and instantaneous voltage
                                spikes that leap far above the nominal levels. Surges and sags are
                                long-duration events occurring at some point in the distribution
                                network when electrical equipment is routinely turned on or off
                                nearby. The magnitude of the surge or sag depends upon the size of
                                the load being removed from or placed on the network. Sags are often
                                produced by the turning on of electric motors, which have high
                                starting currents. (You've probably noticed lights dimming 
                                <fw type="pageNum"><date when="1983-12">December 1983</date> &#169; Byte Publications Inc. <num rend="bold">37</num></fw>
                                <pb n="38"/>
                                <ptr target="#appe"/>
                                <fw type="pageNum"><num rend="bold">38</num> <date when="1983-12">December 1983</date> &#169; Byte Publications Inc.</fw>
                                <pb n="39"/>
                                <cb n="p39_c1"/> when an air conditioner comes on.)</p>
                            <p> Surges are generally the result of network switching by the utility
                                or of a sudden reduction in demand for power in the network; during
                                the period necessary for the utility's electromechanical
                                compensation system to function, an overvoltage transient condition
                                can exist. The most damaging power-line disturbance is the
                                high-speed, highenergy voltage spike. People speaking <cb n="p39_c2"
                                /> loosely about <emph>"power-line transients"</emph> are probably
                                talking about this type of event. Lasting usually less than <measure type="time">100
                                microseconds</measure>, spikes can be up to <measure type="voltage">6000 volts</measure>. Such high-energy
                                transients are produced by the switching off of inductive loads by
                                the opening of switch contacts, short circuits, or blown fuses;
                                severe network load changes; or lightning. Inductive-load switching
                                accounts for the majority of spikes. </p>
                                <fw type="pageNum"><date when="1983-12">December 1983</date> &#169; Byte Publications Inc. <num rend="bold">39</num></fw>
                            <pb n="40"/>
                            <ptr target="#IM2" type="image"/>
                            <ptr target="#IM3" type="image"/>
                            <ptr target="#IM4" type="image"/>
                            <cb n="p40_c1"/>
                            <p> When the coil of an inductive load such as a transformer or motor is
                                suddenly deenergized, the collapsing magnetic field must dissipate
                                its energy, and it does this by placing a large voltage back into
                                the circuit that energized it. Let's examine the process in detail.
                                As the circuit through the inductor is broken, current in the
                                inductor continues to flow, charging the distributed capacitance in
                                the windings. At some point, the charge voltage becomes sufficient
                                to leap across the switch gap as a spark. This sudden shorting
                                action discharges the winding's capacitive charge back into the
                                circuit until the spark ceases. This process repeats in a cycle
                                until there is too little energy left in the coil to create an arc
                                across the contacts. The waveform of inductance-generated transients
                                is oscillatory. For example, a contact opening while conducting <measure type="current">100
                                mA</measure> <term ref="#mA" rend="italic">(milliamperes)</term> in a <measure type="inductance">1-H</measure>
                                    <term ref="#henry" rend="italic">(henry)</term> inductance
                                will produce a <measure type="voltage">3000-V</measure> spike, assuming about a <measure type="capacitivity">0.001-&#181;tF</measure> <term
                                    ref="#muF" rend="italic">(microfarad)</term> stray winding
                                capacitance. Whenever you plug in a vacuum cleaner, hair drier, or
                                other appliance (even your computer), you could be creating some
                                potentially serious transient disruptions for other equipment on the
                                same power line. The equipment need not even be on the same wiring
                                circuit. The capacitance of household wiring is often sufficient to
                                couple a transient from one wire to another <term ref="#diffMode"
                                    >(differential mode)</term> or from the wire to the ground <term
                                    ref="#commMode">(common mode)</term>. Lightning is the most
                                violent and most destructive source of transient energy. A direct
                                lightning hit is catastrophic, but direct hits seldom occur. A more
                                frequent danger is that a lightning strike on a power line miles
                                away may result in a thousandvolt spike rushing throughout your
                                home. Such hits happen frequently enough to cause much grief.</p>
                            <p> (Because lightning is such a significant source of transients, I've
                                explained it in detail in the text box <ref target="#appe">"How
                                    Lightning Strikes."</ref> A secondary, and more widespread,
                                effect of a lightning hit on a power line is a voltage sag over a
                                large part of the 
                                <fw type="pageNum"><num rend="bold">40</num> <date when="1983-12">December 1983</date> &#169; Byte Publications Inc.</fw>
                                <pb n="41"/>
                                <ptr target="#IM5" type="image"/>
                                <ptr target="#IM6" type="image"/>
                                <cb n="p41_c1"/> network as the power company's safety circuits
                                compensate for the spike.) </p>
                        </item>
                        <label rend="bold">Electrical noise.</label>
                        <item>
                            <p> Miscellaneous electrical noise is the final source of power-line
                                disturbances. It is best understood as high-voltage highfrequency
                                interference. Noise in the range from <measure type="frequency">10 kHz</measure> <term ref="#kHz"
                                    rend="italic">(kilohertz)</term> to <measure type="frequency">50 MHz</measure> <term ref="#MHz"
                                    rend="italic">(megahertz)</term> is the most common cause of
                                computer failures. Because of its frequency, noise can be either
                                broadcast through free space from its source or conducted directly
                                through the power lines. Digital electronic equipment is a prime
                                source of high-frequency noise. </p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                 <!--Summary section 3: The author speaks about the powerline protection you might use.-->
                <div type="sezione" n="3">
                    <head rend="bold">Power-Line Protection.</head>
                    <p> I'm not trying to make you afraid to plug your computer into the wall
                        outlet. There are remedies for virtually all the problems I've mentioned,
                        although some are more practical for some computer users than others. If
                        surges or sags are a constant problem for you, you can try having the power
                        company change the tap on your local step-down transformer or installing a
                        constant-voltage transformer on your premises. These measures, although
                        expensive, are effective. If you are plagued by blackouts or have equipment
                        that should never be shut down, I suggest that you consider obtaining an
                            <term ref="#UPS">uninterruptible power supply</term>, abbreviated <choice><abbr>UPS</abbr><expan>Uninterruptible Power Supply</expan></choice>.
                        Using a <choice><abbr>UPS</abbr><expan>Uninterruptible Power Supply</expan></choice> gives you confidence in the quality of your power and
                        effectively isolates your computer from damaging perturbations. However, a
                        <choice><abbr>UPS</abbr><expan>Uninterruptible Power Supply</expan></choice> is also quite costly. In the case of electrical noise and <choice><abbr>EMI</abbr><expan>ElectroMagnetic Interference</expan></choice>, there are
                        filters and construction techniques that can be employed to reduce
                        interference, but a better answer is to find the pollution at the source and
                        eliminate it. My article in the <date when="1981-01">January 1981</date>
                        <name>BYTE</name> outlined most methods of filtration and preventive design.
                        While I'll try not to belabor the point, a power-line filter is an important
                        noise- and transient-suppression device. The best answer to transients is to
                        suppress their voltages to a harmless level, either with filters or a
                        special category of components called <soCalled rend="italic"> transient suppressors.</soCalled>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <cb n="p41_c2"/>
                 <!--In the next 3 sections: The author speaks in details about the main protections you can use against powerline's pollution.-->
                <div type="sezione" n="4">
                    <head rend="bold">Power-Line Filters</head>
                    <p> A power-line interference filter is an electronic circuit used to control
                        <choice><abbr>RFI</abbr><expan>Radio Frequency Interference</expan></choice> and <choice><abbr>EMI</abbr><expan>ElectroMagnetic Interference</expan></choice> conducted into and out of equipment. The filter is intended to
                        provide unwanted interference signals with a high series impedance (into the
                        vulnerable equipment) and low shunt impedance (to ground). It generally
                        consists of a set of passive components that act as a mismatching network
                        for high-frequency signals-a low-pass filter. The network attenuates <choice><abbr>RF</abbr><expan>Radio Frequency</expan></choice>
                        energy above <measure type="frequency">10 kHz</measure>, while passing the <measure type="frequency">60-Hz</measure> power.</p>
                    <p> The simplest possible filter is a single capacitor wired in parallel or <cb
                            n="p41_c3"/> a single coil wired in series with the power line. More
                        typically, several <term ref="#cond">capacitors</term> and/or coils are
                        used together, connected into different configurations variously called L,
                        &#8508;, and T filters. Though containing only a few components, such <term ref="#pasBilNet">passive
                        bilateral networks</term> have complex transfer characteristics that are extremely
                        dependent upon the impedances of the source and load. Because you can't
                        predict these impedances for all applications, it is not possible to
                        unequivocally state that a specific filter configuration will work the same
                        way in two different environments. But to allow 
                        <fw type="pageNum"><date when="1983-12">December 1983</date> &#169; Byte Publications Inc. <num rend="bold">41</num></fw>
                        <pb n="42"/>
                        <ptr target="#IM7" type="image"/>
                        <ptr target="#IM8" type="image"/>
                        <cb n="p42_c1"/> electrical specifications to be minimally compared,
                        however, resistive source and load impedances of <measure unit="Ω">50 ohms</measure> each are generally
                        used. Two similar power-line filters, even built with the same circuit
                        topology and component values, may not perform identically; the mounting and
                        wiring of the filter can be critical influences on its performance. A
                        power-line filter is best installed at the point in your equipment where the
                        power line comes inside the case rather than at the far end of a long cord.
                        The filter's purpose is to attenuate high-frequency signals: this purpose is
                        defeated if these parasitic signals can gain access to the equipment by
                        capacitively coupling to the power cord at a point behind the filter. It's
                        not always possible to disassemble your computer to add a line filter, but
                        the best location for a power-line filter is bolted to the chassis of the
                        electronic equipment it protects, or at least in the immediate vicinity,
                        such as at the power receptacle. While you could construct a line filter
                        using the formulas and designs from a magazine article, I heartily recommend
                        that you buy a packaged <cb n="p42_c2"/>unit instead.</p>
                    <p> The selection is easier and much more controlled using commercial line
                        filters <ref target="#addrCom">(see the text box on page 39)</ref>. So much
                        depends upon component selection and layout that the only way to make sure
                        power-line interference has been eliminated is to actually test the filter
                        in your equipment. <cb n="p42_c3"/> A circuit designed according to theory
                        using a <measure unit="Ω">50-ohm</measure> assumed impedance probably won't work as well as one
                        empirically derived using the actual equipment and power line.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="sezione" n="5">
                    <head rend="bold">Transient Suppressors</head>
                    <p> Protection from. the various kinds of line transients is obtained by
                        suppressing or diverting them. The three types of circuits most often used
                        for this are filters, <term ref="#crowB">crowbars</term>, and <term ref="#VolClamp">voltage-clampers</term>. As I previously alluded,
                        filters comprising inductances and capacitances are widely used for
                        interference protection, including transients. Since most transient signals
                        are high frequency, the suppression by a filter is often effective, provided
                        it can withstand the associated high voltages.</p>
                    <p> Crowbar circuits use a switching action, such as turning on a thyristor or
                        arcing across a spark gap, to divert transients. But <term ref="#crowB">crowbars</term> that
                        incorporate <abbr>SCRs</abbr>
                        <expan>(silicon-controlled rectifiers)</expan> and triacs are much too slow
                        to effectively suppress <measure type="time">100-&#181;s (microsecond)</measure> transients. Most often they
                        are incorporated in low-voltage <choice>
                            <abbr>DC</abbr>
                            <expan>Direct Current</expan>
                        </choice> power-supply output circuits where overvoltage conditions occur at
                        more manageable speeds (milliseconds). Spark-gap devices, which include
                        carbon blocks and gas tubes, are fast 
                        <fw type="pageNum"><num rend="bold">42</num> <date when="1983-12">December 1983</date> &#169; Byte Publications Inc.</fw>
                        <pb n="43"/>
                        <ptr target="#IM1A" type="image"/>
                        <ptr target="#IM1B" type="image"/>
                        <cb n="p43_c1"/>and effective, but they trigger at relatively high voltages,
                        making them unsuitable as the sole protection for semiconductor
                        circuitry.</p>
                    <p> Voltage-clamping devices, on the other hand, have impedances that vary as a
                        function of either the voltage across or the current through them. The
                        circuit being protected is unaffected by the presence of the clamping device
                        unless the incoming supply voltage exceeds the clamping level, as would be
                        the case when a transient hits. The various kinds of high-speed
                        voltage-clamping devices include selenium cells, zener diodes,
                        silicon-carbide varistors, and metaloxide varistors. Of these, the
                        metaloxide varistors, or <choice><abbr>MOVs</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistors</expan></choice>, hold a Significant price/performance
                        advantage and are highly applicable in personal computing applications.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="sezione" n="6">
                    <head rend="bold"><choice><abbr>MOVs</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistors</expan></choice> to the Rescue</head>
                    <p>Metal-Oxide Varistors are voltagedependent nonlinear devices that behave
                        somewhat like a back-biased zener diode. When a voltage lower than its
                        conduction threshold is applied across it, the <choice><abbr>MOV</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistor</expan></choice> appears as a
                        nonconducting open circuit. But if the applied voltage becomes greater than
                        this set point (when a transient hits), the <choice><abbr>MOV</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistor</expan></choice> begins to conduct, clamping
                        the input voltage to a safe level. In effect, the <choice><abbr>MOV</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistor</expan></choice> absorbs the transient
                        and dissipates the energy as heat.</p>
                    <p> An <choice><abbr>MOV</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistor</expan></choice> is made of zinc oxide combined with small amounts of bismuth, cobalt,
                        and manganese. The individual zinc-oxide grains form many p/n
                        (positive-doped/negativedoped) junctions that combine in a multitude of
                        series and parallel arrangements. This diversity of microstructure causes
                        its nonlinear semiconducting characteristics. An <choice><abbr>MOV</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistor</expan></choice> is inherently more
                        rugged than a single-junction semiconductor device (a zener diode, for
                        example) because energy is uniformly absorbed throughout the bulk of the
                        component.</p>
                    <p> The physical dimensions of the <choice><abbr>MOV</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistor</expan></choice> determine its characteristics, its
                        conduction-threshold voltage varying as a function of thickness, and its
                        energy-dissipating capacity varying <cb n="p43_c2"/> according to
                        volume.</p>
                    <p> <choice><abbr>MOVs</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistors</expan></choice> are available in operating voltages from <measure type="voltage">6 to 2800 V</measure>, with peak current
                        capacities of up to <measure type="current">50,000 A (amperes)</measure>. <choice><abbr>MOVs</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistors</expan></choice> respond to transients in only
                        a few nanoseconds and are relatively inexpensive. The chief producer of <choice><abbr>MOVs</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistors</expan></choice>
                        is the <orgName>General Electric Company</orgName>.</p>
                </div>
                <!--Summary section 7: An incentive to protect your computer and to read his (author) precedent article.
                 And a little guide to which protection choose.-->
                <div type="sezione" n="7">
                    <head rend="bold">Protect Your Computer</head>
                    <p>Large companies sometimes solve power-line problems by producing their own
                        power. In the home or small office, it's more practical to protect your
                        computer and peripherals through comprehensive application of filtering and
                        transient suppression. Most of the commercially available filtered power
                        strips contain <choice><abbr>MOVs</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistors</expan></choice> as their primary suppression device. Even those costing
                        <measure type="currency">$50 or $75</measure> rarely contain more than <measure type="currency">$5</measure> worth of transient protection. By
                        purchasing the suppression components separately and installing them
                        yourself, you can save a lot of money.<cb n="p43_c3"/>The majority of the
                        projects I've presented in <name>Circuit Cellar</name> articles can be built
                        for <measure type="currency">$50 to $2000</measure>, but the project this month wins hands down for economy.
                        For the most part, line filters and <choice><abbr>MOVs</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistors</expan></choice> are available off the shelf, and
                        adequate transient suppression for your computer might cost as little as
                        <measure type="currency">$1.59!</measure></p>
                    <p> You can take two approaches in installing suppression. If you are interested
                        in protecting only a few items of equipment, <choice><abbr>MOVs</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistors</expan></choice> can be wired across the AC
                        line where it enters the enclosures. You can find the <orgName>General Electric</orgName>
                        V130LA10A <choice><abbr>MOV</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistor</expan></choice> component at <orgName>Radio Shack</orgName> for <measure type="currency">$1.59</measure> (stock number 276-570).
                        This device is ideally suited to <objectName>120-VAC</objectName> applications. It has an energy
                        rating of <measure type="energy">38 joules</measure> (watt-seconds) and will clamp to <measure type="voltage">340 V</measure> at <measure type="current">50 A</measure> within <measure type="time">35
                        ns (nanoseconds)</measure>. Its peak-current rating is <measure type="current">4500 A</measure>. (For heavier duties,
                        you'll need to use V130LA20A or V130PA20A <choice><abbr>MOV</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistor</expan></choice>.) (As a rule, if you are
                        going to be 
                        <fw type="pageNum"><date when="1983-12">December 1983</date> &#169; Byte Publications Inc. <num rend="bold">43</num></fw>
                        <pb n="44"/><fw type="header">Circle 239 on inquiry card.</fw><cb n="p44_c1"/><ptr target="#AdvIng"/><cb n="p44_c2"/> working inside the equipment you
                        should also install line filters. You can buy <orgName>Corcom</orgName> type-5VK1 5-A <choice><abbr>RFI</abbr><expan>Radio Frequency Interference</expan></choice>
                        power-line filters at <orgName>Radio Shack</orgName> for <measure type="currency">$11.95</measure> (stock number 273-100). These
                        units, like the one shown in <ref target="#IM1">photo 1<graphic
                                url="./img/fig1.png"/></ref>, are adequate for most consumer
                        applications and fit in very nicely with existing equipment.)</p>
                    <p> The easier alternative is to modify a regular power strip to include
                        transient suppression. <orgName>Radio Shack</orgName>'s 4- outlet strip (number 61-2620,
                        costing <measure type="currency">$15.95</measure>) is perfect for this application. Merely open it up and
                        install three <choice><abbr>MOVs</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistors</expan></choice>, as demonstrated in the series of photos 2 through 6,
                        connected as shown in <ref target="#IM1">figure 1<graphic url="./img/fig1.png"/>
                        </ref>. One <choice><abbr>MOV</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistor</expan></choice> is installed directly between the black (hot) and
                        white (neutral) leads, the second <choice><abbr>MOV</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistor</expan></choice> is connected from the black lead to
                        the green (ground) wire, and the third from the white to the green. While
                        you might squeak through by installing one <choice><abbr>MOV</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistor</expan></choice> across the line, complete
                        <term ref="#commMode">common-mode</term> and <term ref="#diffMode">differential-mode</term> suppression requires three <choice><abbr>MOVs</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistors</expan></choice>. (<ref
                            target="#IM7">Photo 7<graphic url="./img/fig7.png"/></ref> shows a
                        commercial adaptation of the simplified scheme.) The price for all the parts
                        of the protected power strip is <measure type="currency">$20.72</measure>. If you were to buy a larger power
                        strip or build your own distribution box, you could also add a power-line
                        filter. And if you have a filter strip already on your computer, you might
                        want to check its degree of transient protection (see <ref target="#IM8"
                            >photo 8<graphic url="./img/fig8.png"/></ref>).</p>
                </div>
                <!--Conclusive section, it could be inserted in conclusion, but the author had created a subtitle for this section.-->
                <div type="sezione" n="8">
                    <head rend="bold">An Ounce of Prevention...</head>
                    <p>This project may not seem very exciting. I didn't find the idea very
                        exciting, either, until the flash and subsequent smoke coming out of my
                        favorite article-writing computer provided all the excitement I'll need for
                        months. Most of the <measure type="currency">$3000</measure> worth of damage I had was for equipment plugged
                        into a single circuit, some of it on the same power strip. I had always
                        known the protective value of <choice><abbr>MOVs</abbr><expan>Metal Oxide Varisistors</expan></choice>, but I thought it wouldn't happen to me.
                        A few dollars' worth of parts could have saved a lot of aggravation. Voltage
                        spikes and power-line disturbances aren't always the result of storm
                        activity. Transient-caused equipment failures can happen any-<cb n="p44_c3"/>time.</p>
                    <p>The events I've described just served as a catalyst for presenting the
                        subject. And even if lightning never hits you, you should know that many of
                        the new computers I have been evaluating this year have shown an increased
                        sensitivity to external interferance, including power-line <term ref="#gltch">glitches</term>. You
                        wouldn't want to find your new computer rebooting suddenly at a critical
                        point or discover the memory to be scrambled after you plug in a printer on
                        the same outlet. Transient suppression constitutes an ounce of prevention.
                        You can spend thousands for the cure. </p>
                </div>
                <!--Other information usually inserted at the end of an article-->
                <div type="conclusion">
                    <div>
                        <head>Next Month</head>
                        <p> A new integrated circuit from <orgName>National Semiconductor</orgName> pennits an intelligent
                            video-display tenninal to be built from only 21 chips. &#9632;</p>
                        <p> To receive a complete list of Ciarcia 's <name>Circuit Cellar</name> project kits available
                            from the Micromint, circle 100 on the reader service inquiry card at the back of
                            the magazine. </p>
                        <p> <persName ref="#auth" xml:lang="en"><forename>Steve</forename> <surname>Ciarcia</surname></persName> (pronounced "see-ARE-see-ah") is an electronics engineer and
                            computer consultant with experience in process control, digital design, nuclear
                            instrumentation, product development, and marketing. In addition to writing for
                            BYTE, he has published several books. He can be contacted at 
                            <address rend="italic">
                                <street>POB <num>582</num>,Glastonbury,</street>
                                <postCode>CT 06033.</postCode>
                            </address>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="references">
                        <head rend="bold">References</head>
                        <p xml:id="refe1">1. <persName><surname>Ciarcia</surname>, <forename>Steve</forename></persName>. "A Computer-Controlled Wood Stove." <date when="1980-02">February 1980</date> BYTE,
                            page 32.</p>
                        <p xml:id="refe2"> 2. <persName><surname>Ciarcia</surname>, <forename>Steve</forename></persName>. "Electromagnetic Interference." <date when="1981-01">January 1981</date> BYTE, page
                            48.</p>
                        <p xml:id="refe3"> 3. <persName><surname>Roberts</surname>, <forename>Steven K</forename></persName>. Industrial Design with Microcomputers. Englewood
                            Cliffs, NJ: Prentice-Hall, <date when="1982">1982</date>.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="advert">
                        <head rend="bold">Editor's Note:</head>
                        <p><persName ref="#auth" xml:lang="en">Steve</persName> often refers to previous <name>Circuit Cellar</name> articles as reference material
                        for each month's current article. Most of these past articles are available
                        in reprint books from BYTE Books, <orgName>McGraw-Hill Book Company</orgName>, POB 400,
                        Hightstown, NJ 08250. Ciarcia's <name>Circuit Cellar</name>, Volume I cavers articles
                        that appeared in BYTE from <date when="1977-09">September 1977</date> through <date when="1978-11">November 1978</date>. Ciarcia's
                        <name>Circuit Cellar</name>, Volume II contains articles from <date when="1978-12">December 1978</date> through <date when="1980-06">June
                        1980</date>. Ciarcia's <name>Circuit Cellar</name>, Volume III contains articles from <date when="1980-07">July 1980</date>
                        through <date when="1978-12">December 1981</date>. Ciarcia's <name>Circuit Cellar</name>, Volume IV, soon to appear,
                        will contain articles from <date when="1982-01">January 1982</date> through <date when="1983-06">June 1983</date>.</p>
                    </div>
                    <fw type="pageNum"><num rend="bold">44</num> <date when="1983-12">December 1983</date> &#169; Byte Publications Inc.</fw>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <!--An author's section to explain the lightning effects on power-line.-->
            <div type="appendix" xml:id="appe">
                <pb n="38"/>
                <cb n="p38_c1"/>
                <head>How Lightning Strikes</head>
                <div type="introduction">
                    <p>A lightning flash is characterized by one or more strokes with typical peak
                        currents of <measure type="current">20 kA</measure> <term ref="#kA">(kiloamperes)</term> or higher. In the immediate vicinity of the
                        stroke's impact on the earth, hazardous voltage gradients exist. It is
                        difficult to establish a definite <cb n="p38_c2"/>grounding-conductance
                        value necessary to protect equipment and personnel. The current in a
                        lightning strike is so high that even <measure type="resistence" unit="Ω">1 ohm</measure> of resistance can theoretically
                        produce hazardous potentials. When lightning strikes a building unprotected
                        by a lightning rod, the stroke seeks out the lowest-impedance path to earth
                        (most likely through the electric wiring or water pipes).</p>
                </div>
                <figure xml:id="appeIm">
                    <graphic url="./img/appendice.png"/>
                    <figDesc> The important element in lightning protection is the lightning rod, a
                        pointed shaft of copper to which a <measure type="volume" unit="in">half-inch</measure> copper cable is fastened. The
                        cable in run down the side of the building, where it is clamped to an
                        <measure type="length" quantity="8.5">8&#189;-foot</measure> copper-plated steel rod driven into the earth. The rod system
                        pictured here costs <measure type="currency">$150</measure>. </figDesc>
                </figure>
                <cb n="p38_c3"/>
                <div type="sezione" n="9">
                    <head rend="bold">How It Starts</head>
                    <p>As the electric charge builds up in a cloud, the electric field in the
                        vicinity of the charge center increases to the point where the air starts to
                        ionize. A column of ionized air, called a <term ref="#pltStamr">pilot streamer</term>, begins to extend
                        toward the earth at a velocity of about <measure>100 miles per hour</measure>. After the <term ref="#pltStamr">pilot
                        streamer</term> has moved perhaps <measure type="length">100 feet to 150 feet</measure>, a more intense discharge
                        called the stepped leader occurs. This discharge inserts additional negative
                        cluzrge into the region around the <term ref="#pltStamr">pilot streamer</term> and allows the <term ref="#pltStamr">pilot
                        streamer</term> to advance for another <measure type="length">100 to 150 feet</measure>, after which the cycle
                        repeats. As its name indicates, the stepped leader progresses toward the
                        earth in a series of steps, with a time interval between steps on the order
                        of <measure type="time">50 microseconds</measure>. </p>
                    <p> In a cloud-to-ground flash, the <term ref="#pltStamr">pilot steamer</term> does not move in a direct line
                        toward the earth but instead follows the path through the atmosphere where
                        the air ionizes most readily. Although the general direction is toward the
                        earth, the specific angle of departure taken by each succeeding <term ref="#pltStamr">pilot
                        streamer</term> from the tip of the previous streamer is unpredictable. Therefore,
                        each <measure type="length">100- to 150-foot</measure> segment of the stroke will likely approach the earth
                        at a different angle. This changing angle of approach gives the overall
                        flash its characteristic <distinct type="ps_slang">zigzag</distinct> appearance.</p>
                    <p> As a highly ionized column, the stepped leader is at essentially the same
                        potential as the charged area from which it originates. Thus, as the stepped
                        leader approaches the earth, the voltage gradient between the earth and the
                        tip of the leader increases. The increasing voltage further encourages the
                        air dielectric between the two regions to break down.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="sezione" n="10">
                    <head rend="bold">Attracting Lightning</head>
                    <p>Objects extending above their surroundings are likely to be struck by
                        lightning. Thin metallic structures, such as flag poles, lighting towers,
                        antennas, and overhead wires, offer a very small cross-sectional area
                        relative to the surrounding terrain, but ample evidence exists to show that
                        such objects apparently attract lightning. The ability of tall structures or
                        objects to attract lightning serves to protect shorter objects and
                        structures nearby. In effect, a tall object establishes a protected zone
                        around it; within this zone, other structures and objects are protected
                        against direct lightning strikes. As the height differen<pb n="39"/><cb
                            n="p39_c1"/>tial between the shorter surrounding objects and the tall
                        one decreases, the protection provided to the shorter objects decreases.
                        Likewise, as the horizontal distance between the tall and short structures
                        increases, the protection afforded by the tall structure decreases.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="sezione" n="11">
                    <head rend="bold">Lightning Rods</head>
                    <p>A protective device that makes use of this phenomenon is the lightning rod,
                        shown in photo. Generally just a sharp copper spike, the lightning rod is
                        attached to the highest point on the structure to be protected. When
                        lightning strikes, the current is shunted directly through a heavy copper
                        wire from the rod to a grounding electrode buried in the earth.
                        Although the duration of a strike is typically less than <measure type="time">2 microseconds</measure>, the
                        voltage generated is high enough to cause flashover strikes to conducting
                        objects located as much as <measure type="length">14 inches</measure> away from the conducting path. For this
                        reason, metallic objects in close proximity to down conductors should be
                        electrically bonded to the conductors.</p>
                    <p> But circuits not in direct contact with the lightning discharge path can
                        experience damage, even in the absence of overt coupling by flashover.
                        Because the high current associated with a discharge builds up so fast,
                        large inductively produced voltages are formed on nearby conductors.
                        Experimental and analytical evidence shows that the surges thus induced can
                        easily exceed the tolerance level of many components, particularly
                        solid-state devices. Inductive surges can be induced by lightning current
                        flowing in a down conductor or structural member, by a stroke to earth in
                        the vicinity of buried cables, or by cloud-to-cloud discharges occurring
                        parallel to long cable runs, either above ground or buried.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="sezione" n="12">
                    <head rend="bold">The Moral</head>
                    <p>The objective of all lightning-protection systems is to direct the high
                        currents away from susceptible elements or limit the voltage gradients
                        developed by the high current to safe levels. In a given area, certain
                        structures or objects are more likely to be struck by lightning than others;
                        however, no object, whether man-made or natural, should be assumed to be
                        immune from lightning. The voltages that could be induced by such discharges
                        present a definite threat to signal and control equipment, particularly
                        equipment employing semiconductor components.</p>
                </div>
                <!--An author's made section for the address where it's possible to buy powerline protections.-->
                <div xml:id="addrCom" type="addressList">
                    <div type="section" n="13">
                        <p>
                            <list>
                                <head rend="bold">Power-Line Conditioner Sources</head>
                                <item><orgName>Cuesta Systems Inc.</orgName>
                                    <address>
                                        <street><num>3440</num> Roberto Court San Luis Obispo, </street>
                                        <postCode>CA 93401</postCode>
                                    </address>
                                    <num>(805) 541-4160</num></item>
                                <item><orgName>Dymarc Industries Inc.</orgName>
                                    <address>
                                        <street><num>21</num> Governor's Court Baltimore,</street>
                                        <postCode>MD 21207</postCode>
                                    </address>
                                    <num>(800) 638-9098</num>
                                    <num>(301) 298-2629</num></item>
                                <item><orgName>Electronic Protection Devices Division CNS Electronics
                                        Corp.</orgName>
                                    <address>
                                        <street><num>5-9</num> Centml Ave. Waltham,</street>
                                        <postCode>MA 02154</postCode>
                                    </address>
                                    <num>(800) 343-1813</num></item>
                                <item><orgName>Electronic Specialists Inc.</orgName>
                                    <address>
                                        <street><num>171</num> South Main St. Natick,</street>
                                        <postCode>MA 07160</postCode>
                                    </address>
                                    <num>(800) 225-4876</num> (orders) <num>(617) 655-1532</num></item>
                                <item><orgName>Isoreg Corporation</orgName>
                                    <address>
                                        <street><num>410</num> Great Rd. Littleton,</street>
                                        <postCode>MA 01460</postCode>
                                    </address>
                                    <num>(617) 486-9483</num></item>
                                <item><orgName>RKS Industries</orgName>
                                    <address>
                                        <street><num>4865</num> Scotts Valley Dr. Scotts
                                            Valley,</street>
                                        <postCode>CA 95066</postCode>
                                    </address>
                                    <num>(800) 892-1342</num>
                                    <num>(408) 438-5760</num></item>
                                <item><orgName>Sun Research Inc.</orgName>
                                    <address>
                                        <street>POB <num>210</num> Old Bay Rd. New Durham,</street>
                                        <postCode>NH 03855</postCode>
                                    </address>
                                    <num>(603) 859-7110</num></item>
                            </list>
                        </p>      
                        <p>
                            <list>
                                <head rend="bold">Power-Line Filter Sources</head>
                                <item><orgName>Cornell-Dubilier Electronics</orgName>
                                    <address>
                                        <street>Box <num>B-967</num> New Bedford,</street>
                                        <postCode> MA 02741</postCode>
                                    </address>
                                    <num>(617) 996-8561</num></item>
                                <item><orgName>Corcom Inc.</orgName>
                                    <address>
                                        <street><num>1600</num> Winchester Rd. Libertyville,</street>
                                        <postCode>IL 60048</postCode>
                                    </address>
                                    <num>(312) 680-7400</num></item>
                                <item><orgName>Curtis Industries Inc.</orgName>
                                    <address>
                                        <street><num>8300</num> North Tower Ave. Milwaukee,</street>
                                        <postCode>WI 53223</postCode>
                                    </address>
                                    <num>(414) 354-1500</num></item>
                                <item><orgName>Genisco Technology Corporation</orgName>
                                    <address>
                                        <street><num>18435</num> Susana Rd. Rancho Dominguez,</street>
                                        <postCode> CA 90221</postCode>
                                    </address>
                                    <num>(213) 537-4750</num></item>
                                <item><orgName>Hopkins Engineering Company</orgName>
                                    <address>
                                        <street><num>12900</num> Foothill Blvd. San Fernando,</street>
                                        <postCode>CA '91342</postCode>
                                    </address>
                                    <num>(213) 361-8691</num></item>
                                <item><orgName>The Potter Company Division of Varian</orgName>
                                    <address>
                                        <street>POB <num>337</num> Wesson,</street>
                                        <postCode>MI 39191</postCode>
                                    </address>
                                    <num>(601) 643-2215</num></item>
                                <item><orgName>Siemens Corporation</orgName>
                                    <address>
                                        <street><num>8700</num> East Thomas Rd. Scottsdale,</street>
                                        <postCode>AZ 85252</postCode>
                                    </address>
                                    <num>(602) 941-6366</num></item>
                                <item><orgName>Sprague Electric Company</orgName>
                                    <address>
                                        <street><num>87</num> Marshall St. North Adams,</street>
                                        <postCode>MA 01247</postCode>
                                    </address>
                                    <num>(413) 664-4411</num></item>
                                <item><orgName>Stanford Applied Engineering</orgName>
                                    <address>
                                        <street><num>3520</num> De La Cruz Blvd. Santa Clara,</street>
                                        <postCode>CA 95050-1997</postCode>
                                    </address>
                                    <num>(408) 988-0700</num></item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <!--Section with adverts-->
            <div xml:id="AdvIng" type="advertising">
                <head rend="underline">COMPUTERS</head>
                <div type="section" n="14">
                    <p><lb/><seg rend="bold">Packages: Create your own</seg>
                    <lb/><seg rend="bold">configuration. CALL</seg></p>
                    <list>
                        <lb/><label rend="bold">IBM PC:</label>
                        <item>
                            (in Slack) 256k. (2) 320k disk
                            drives. Monochrome Display <lb/>&amp; Controller with printer port. C.
                            Itoh F10-40ps letter quality printer, <lb/>Diagnostic &amp; Basic manuals
                            . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$4999</measure>
                        </item>
                        <lb/><label rend="bold">COLUMBIA MPC 1600-1: </label>
                        <item>
                            128k. (2) 320k disk drives. Amber or <lb/>Green video display and controller. (2) serial
                            &amp; (1) parallel port. C. <lb/>Itoh F10-40cps letter qual. prnter.,
                            <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$3000</measure> of free software <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$3999</measure>
                        </item>
                        <lb/><label rend="bold">COLUMBIA HARD DISK MPC 1600-4: </label> 
                        <item>
                            XT Compatible 128k, <lb/>(1) 320k disk drive. 10meg Hard disk drive. Amber
                            or Green video <lb/>display and conlroller. (2) serial &amp; (1) parallel
                            port. C. Itoh F10-<lb/>40cps letter quality printer, and <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$3000</measure> of free
                            software .... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$5699</measure>
                        </item>
                        <lb/><label rend="bold">COLUMBIA PORTABLE COMPUTER VP:</label> 
                        <item>
                            128k. (2) 320k 
                            <lb/>half height disk drives. Monochrome display and controller. (1)
                            <lb/>serial &amp; (1) parallel port. C. ltoh F10-40cps letter qualily printer, and 
                            <lb/><measure type="currency" rend="bold">$3000</measure> of free soltware .................................<measure type="currency" rend="bold">$3795</measure>
                        </item>
                        <lb/><label rend="bold">EAGLE PC- 2:</label>
                        <item>
                            128k. (2) 320k disk drives.
                            monochrome display &amp; <lb/>conlroller. (2) serial &amp; (1) parallel
                            port. DKIDATA 92a near letter <lb/>quality printer, with free software .
                            ...................... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$3399</measure>
                        </item>
                        <lb/><label rend="bold">APPLE IIe:</label>
                        <item>
                            128k, 80 columns display, Amber
                            or Green screen, half <lb/>height disk drive &amp; controller, Fan and
                            electrical surge protector, <lb/>Gemini Star 10X dot matrix printer
                            .................... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$2199</measure>
                        </item>
                        <lb/><label rend="bold">CANON AS100 </label>
                        <item>
                            128k, (2) 640k disk drives
                            &amp; controller. color dis-<lb/>play. (1) parallel port. with color
                            printer ............ <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$3599</measure>
                        </item>
                        <lb/><label rend="bold">DEC RAINBOW 100:</label>
                        <item>
                            64k, (1) dual disk drive.
                            Monochrome dis-<lb/>play, keyboard. MSDOS or CP/M 86 operating system. DEC
                            LA50-<lb/>RA dol matrix printer ......... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$3799</measure>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="15">
                    <head rend="underline">IBM PC &amp; COMPATIBLE ACCESSORIES</head>
                    <p>
                      <cb n="1"/>
                      <lb n="1"/>64k memory chips...... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$92</measure>
                      <lb n="2"/>additional disk drives <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$450</measure>
                      <lb n="3"/>DOS 1.1 .............. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$40</measure>
                      <lb n="4"/>DOS 2.0 .............. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$60</measure>
                      <lb n="5"/>Easywriter ........... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$165</measure>
                      <lb n="6"/>Visicalc ............. CALL
                      <lb n="7"/>dBASE II ............. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$430</measure>
                      <cb n="2"/>
                      <lb n="1"/>PFS report ...... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$133</measure>
                      <lb n="2"/>PFS filter ...... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$110</measure>
                      <lb n="3"/>TK! Solver ...... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$250</measure>
                      <lb n="4"/>WordStar ........ <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$327</measure>
                      <lb n="5"/>MailMerge ....... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$165</measure>
                      <lb n="6"/>Memorex disks ... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$3.25</measure>
                      <lb n="7"/>3M disk ......... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$2.99</measure>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="16">
                    <head rend="underline">APPLE IIe &amp; COMPATIBLE ACCESSORIES</head>
                    <p>
                      <cb n="1"/>
                      <lb n="1"/><seg rend="bold">JAGUAR half height</seg>
                      <lb n="2"/>drives ................. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$249</measure>
                      <lb n="3"/><seg rend="bold">MICRO·SCI full height</seg>
                      <lb n="4"/>drives ................. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$220</measure>
                      <lb n="5"/>80 column cards ........ <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$275</measure>
                      <lb n="6"/>80 column with 64k cards <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$375</measure>
                      <cb n="2"/>
                      <lb n="1"/>Grappler ............... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$140</measure>
                      <lb n="2"/>System Saver Fan ....... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$55</measure>
                      <lb n="3"/>WordStar ............... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$327</measure>
                      <lb n="4"/>dBASE .................. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$430</measure>
                      <lb n="5"/>Memorex disks .......... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$3.25</measure>
                      <lb n="6"/>3M disks .................. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$2.99</measure>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="17">
                    <head rend="underline">PRINTERS</head>
                    <cb n="1"/>
                    <list>
                        <head><orgName rend="bold">DOT MATRIX</orgName></head>
                        <item>
                            <lb/> C. Itoh ProWriter .... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$440</measure>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <lb/><orgName rend="bold">OKIDATA</orgName>
                            <lb/> MICROLINE 82a ....... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$440</measure>
                            <lb/> MICROLINE 92 ........ <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$499</measure>
                            <lb/> MICROLINE 93 ........ <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$789</measure>
                            <lb/> RIBBONS ............. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$4.99</measure>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <list>
                        <head rend="bold"> LETTER QUALITY </head>
                        <item>
                            <lb/><orgName rend="bold">C. IT0H</orgName>
                            <lb/> F10-40cps ......... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$1199</measure>
                            <lb/> F10-55cps ......... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$1499</measure>
                            <lb/> Single sheet feeder <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$695</measure>
                            <lb/> Tractor feed ...... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$275</measure>
                            <lb/> Ribbons-multistrike <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$6.99</measure>
                            <lb/> Ribbons-nylon ..... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$7.99</measure>
                            <lb/><seg rend="bold"> NEC 3550</seg> ... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$1899</measure>
                            <cb n="2"/>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <lb/><orgName rend="bold">GEMINI</orgName>
                            <lb/> STAR 10X ... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$335</measure>
                            <lb/> STAR 15 ........... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$490</measure>
                            <lb/> RIBBONS ........... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$4.99</measure>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <lb/><orgName rend="bold">TRANSTAR</orgName>
                            <lb/>T315 COLOR PRINTER . <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$499</measure>
                            <lb/> Ribbon ............ <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$14.95</measure>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <lb/><orgName rend="bold">DIABLO</orgName>
                            <lb/> 620 ............... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$999</measure>
                            <lb/> 630 ............... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$1999</measure>
                            <lb/> Single sheet feeder <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$1350</measure>
                            <lb/> Tractor leed ...... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$215</measure>
                            <lb/> Ribbons-multistrike <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$6.99</measure>
                            <lb/> Ribbons-nylon ..... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$7.99</measure>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <lb/><seg rend="bold">TTX-1014</seg> ...... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$499</measure>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <lb/><seg rend="bold">SMITH CORONA TP-1</seg> .. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$499</measure>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="18">
                    <head rend="underline">MONITORS</head>
                    <list>
                        <head><orgName rend="bold">ZENITH</orgName></head>
                        <item> 121 .. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$93</measure></item>
                        <item> 122 .. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$129</measure></item>
                        <item> 123 .. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$139</measure></item>
                    </list>
                    <list>
                        <head><orgName rend="bold">TAXAN</orgName></head>
                        <item> RGB I .. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$325</measure></item>
                        <item> RGB II .. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$520</measure></item>
                        <item> GREEN .. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$159</measure></item>
                        <item> AMBER .. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$169</measure></item>
                    </list>
                    <list>
                        <head><orgName rend="bold">AMDEK</orgName></head>
                        <item> COLOR I .. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$299</measure></item>
                        <item> COLOR II .. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$429</measure></item>
                    </list>
                    <lb/><p><orgName rend="bold">GORILLA</orgName> HI-RES GREEN .. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$99</measure></p>
                    <lb/><p><orgName rend="bold">PRINCETON</orgName> GraphicSys .. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">$665</measure></p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="19">
                    <head rend="underline">SOFTWARE</head>
                    <cb n="1"/>
                    <list>
                        <head rend="bold"><orgName>APPLE</orgName> SOFTWARE</head>
                        <item>
                            <lb n="1"/> Temple of Apshai ... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">29.99</measure>
                            <lb n="2"/> DOS Boss ........... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">19.99</measure>
                            <lb n="3"/> Type faces ......... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">14.99</measure>
                            <lb n="4"/> Apple Panic ........ <measure type="currency" rend="bold">21.95</measure>
                            <lb n="5"/> Chopliner .. . ..... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">24.95</measure>
                            <lb n="6"/> Raster Blaster ..... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">21.95</measure>
                            <lb n="7"/> Ultima ............. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">29.95</measure>
                            <lb n="8"/> MicroWave .......... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">24.97</measure>
                            <lb n="9"/> Swashbuckler ....... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">23.95</measure>
                            <lb n="10"/> Zaxxon ............. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">26.95</measure>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <list>
                        <head rend="bold"><orgName>IBM</orgName> PC SOFTWARE</head>
                        <item>
                            <lb n="11"/><orgName rend="bold">ALPHA SOFTWARE</orgName>
                            <lb n="12"/> Database ........... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">99.97</measure>
                            <lb n="13"/> <orgName>Apple</orgName>-<orgName>IBM</orgName> CnnCtn ... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">136.75</measure>
                            <lb n="14"/> Data Base Manager .. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">191.75</measure>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <lb n="15"/><orgName rend="bold">ASHTON-TATE</orgName>
                            <lb n="16"/>Financial Planner <measure type="currency" rend="bold">430.00</measure>
                            <lb n="17"/> Bottom Line Strtgst ...... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">250.00</measure>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <lb n="17"/> <orgName rend="bold">EPYX</orgName>
                            <lb n="18"/> Temple of Apshai .... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">26.95</measure>
                            <lb n="19"/> Crush, Crumble &amp; Chomp <measure type="currency" rend="bold">22.99</measure>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <lb n="20"/> <orgName rend="bold">INFOCOM</orgName> Zork I/II/III .... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">79.00</measure>
                            <cb n="2"/>
                            <lb n="1"/> Sargon II ................ <measure type="currency" rend="bold">24.97</measure>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <lb n="2"/> <orgName rend="bold">MICROPRO</orgName> products WordStar/MailMerge/SpeliStar CalcStar/DataStar/InfoStar
                            <lb n="3"/> LOWEST PRICES ....... CALL
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <lb n="4"/> <orgName rend="bold">MILTON BRADLEY</orgName> educational 
                            <lb n="5"/>software. All about Division,
                            <lb n="6"/> Fractions. Commas. Words.
                            <lb n="7"/> We have Them all ......... CALL
                            <lb n="8"/> Pie Writer IIe ........... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">99.97</measure>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <lb n="9"/><orgName rend="bold">DIGITAL RESEARCH</orgName>
                            <lb n="10"/> CPIM B6 ............. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">42.99</measure>
                            <lb n="11"/> Pascal/MI ........... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">270.00</measure>
                            <lb n="12"/><seg rend="bold"> IU$</seg> Soltware all in stock
                            <lb n="13"/><seg rend="bold"> TIM</seg> III ............. <measure type="currency" rend="bold">302.97</measure>
                            <lb n="14"/> <orgName rend="bold">MICROPRO</orgName> ............ CALL
                            <lb n="15"/> <orgName rend="bold">Microsoft</orgName> Multiplan . <measure type="currency" rend="bold">175.00</measure>
                            <lb n="16"/> Crosstalk ........... <measure type="currency" rend="bold">125.00</measure>
                            <lb n="17"/> <orgName rend="bold">VISICORP</orgName> software
                            <lb n="18"/> Visicalc/Visifile/Visiword, Too
                            <lb n="19"/> Low to Mention ...... CAll
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="bold"> ACCESSORIES: furniture. Modem., Cable., Olsk Cases . .... . CALL</p>
                    <p xml:id="fax_id"><ptr target="#IM9" type="facsimile"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <!--All figures goes here.-->
            <div type="figures">
                <figure xml:id="IM2">
                    <graphic url="./img/fig2.png"/>
                    <figDesc> Photo 2: You can save approximately <measure type="currency">$40</measure> on the price of a
                        transient-protected power strip by adding the protection yourself, as
                        demonstrated on the Radio Shack Archer 61-2620 unit. First, unscrew the end
                        plates. </figDesc>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="IM3">
                    <graphic url="./img/fig3.png"/>
                    <figDesc> Photo 3: Open the strip case, exposing the four receptacles and the
                        white circuit-breaker block. The three wires conducting power run the length
                        of the strip: black is the hot side, white is the neutral return, and the
                        green wire is earth ground. </figDesc>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="IM4">
                    <graphic url="./img/fig4.png"/>
                    <figDesc> Photo 4: Using an X-acto knife or similar tool, strip insulation from
                        the wires between the receptacles (which I number 1 through 4, from left to
                        right) according to the following system: between 1 and 2, strip the green
                        and black; between 2 and 3, strip the green and white; between 3 and 4,
                        strip the black and white. </figDesc>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="IM5">
                    <graphic url="./img/fig5.png"/>
                    <figDesc> Photo 5: You can now solder a varistor between each of the stripped
                        wire pairs, mounting it fiat against the back face of the receptacle so that
                        the case will fit together again. </figDesc>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="IM6">
                    <graphic url="./img/fig6.png"/>
                    <figDesc> Photo 6: The outlet strip with three MOVs installed provides both
                        common-mode and differential-mode transient suppression. After you have
                        finished soldering, carefully reassemble the power strip's enclosure and
                        screw it back together. </figDesc>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="IM7">
                    <graphic url="./img/fig7.png"/>
                    <figDesc> Photo 7: For quicker and easier, though incomplete, protection, you
                        can plug your computer into a simple voltage-spike protector such as the
                        Radio Shack 61-2790. As you can see from the disassembled unit, the
                        metal-oxide varistor (wrapped in fiberglass tape) is connected between only
                        the hot and neutral lines (black and white). It has no varistor connection
                        to the ground lead and therefore does not protect against common-mode
                        transients. </figDesc>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="IM8">
                    <graphic url="./img/fig8.png"/>
                    <figDesc>Photo 8: Some line filters are made to work in specific circumstances.
                        This <orgName>Radio Shack</orgName> powerline- filter strip (stock number 26-1451) was devised
                        to cure interference problems with the <objectName>TRS-80 Model I</objectName> computer; it contains
                        two separate LC (inductancelcapacitance) interference filters but no
                        varistors. If you have this strip, I suggest you install some MOVs.
                    </figDesc>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="IM1A">
                    <graphic url="./img/fig1a.png"/>
                    <figDesc> Figure la: The <orgName>Radio</orgName> Shack four-outlet power strip can be easily
                        modified to protect equipment from high-energy power-line transients. Three
                        General Electric V130LA10A metal-oxide varistors (MOVs-<orgName>Radio Shack</orgName> number
                        276-570) are connected between the hot, neutral, and ground wires of the
                        power line. </figDesc>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="IM1B">
                    <graphic url="./img/fig1b.png"/>
                    <figDesc> Figure 1b: For added protection against low-energy electromagnetic and
                        radio-frequency interference, the Corcom 5VK1 line filter (<orgName>Radio Shack</orgName>
                        273-100) can be installed in the circuit. </figDesc>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <!--Floating text here-->
            <div type="chap">
                <epigraph xml:id="epgh">
                    <cit>
                        <quote>An expensive lesson produces the cheapest <name>Circuit Cellar</name>
                            project yet</quote>
                    </cit>
                </epigraph>
                <ab xml:id="cpy" rend="italic"><lb/> Copyright &#169; <date when="1983">1983</date>
                    <persName ref="#auth"><forename>Steven A.</forename>
                        <surname>Ciarcia</surname></persName>. <lb/>All rights reserved.</ab>
            </div>
            <!--Gloss here, under my responsability, because I am the author of this gloss-->
            <respons target="#AM" locus="name value" resp="#my_gloss"/>
            <div xml:id="my_gloss">
                <list type="gloss">
                    <label><term>glitches</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="gltch">A sudden, usually temporary malfunction or irregularity of equipment.</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>pilot streamer</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="pltStamr">A relatively slow-moving, nonluminous lightning streamer,to provide a physical explanation for the observed intermittent mode of advance of a stepped leader as it initiates a cloud-to-ground lightning discharge.</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>voltage-clampers</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="VolClamp">A clamper is an electronic circuit that fixes either the positive or the negative peak excursions of a signal to a defined value by shifting its DC value.</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>crowbars</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="crowB">A crowbar is an electric circuit used for preventing an overvoltage condition of a power supply.</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>passive bilateral networks</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="pasBilNet">A network or circuit in which the magnitude of the current remains the same when the voltage polarity is reversed.</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>source-impedance</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="src-imp">It's called source the device that supplies a voltage signal or a dc power voltage. And its impedance is the internal resistor in series with that otherwise perfect source voltage.</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>sockets</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="sok">Sockets are interface through power line where the device is attached.</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>kiloamperes</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="kA">Measure unit used for current intensity, in Ampere * 10^(3)</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>milliamperes</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="mA">Measure unit used for current intensity, in Ampere * 10^(-3)</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>microfarad</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="muF">Measure unit used for condenser capacitivity, in Farad * 10^(-6)</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>henry</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="henry">Measure unit used for inductance (of circuit) in Henry</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>kilohertz</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="kHz">Measure unit used for frequency, in Hertz * 10^(3)</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>megahertz</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="MHz">Measure unit used for frequency, in Hertz * 10^(6)</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>electromagnetic interference</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="intfM">An interference in telecomunication happened when a signal
                            collide with another. This collision appear when the frequency is the same.
                            In this case the frequency is in a variable spectre, and could be
                            overvoltage.</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>radio-frequency interference</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="intfR">An interference in telecomunication happened when a signal
                            collide with another. This collision appear when the frequency is the same.
                            In this case the frequency is in radio spectre.</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>nominal voltage</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="nomV">Nominal voltage is the quantinty according. The real voltage
                            could be different.</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>uninterruptible power supply</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="UPS">As a battery, UPS is a system to stabilize current and
                            prevent blackouts. Is an electrical apparatus that provides emergency power
                            to load when the input power source or mains power fails.</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>capacitors</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="cond">Capacitors is a passive two-terminal electrical component
                            that stores electrical energy in an electrical field.</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>differential-mode</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="diffMode">Differential mode interference is a signal that appears
                            on two lines of a closed loop, but current flow in opposite
                            directions.</gloss></item>
                    <label><term>common-mode</term></label>
                    <item><gloss xml:id="commMode">A common-mode EMI signal appears on the two signal lines
                            simultaneously in the same direction and phase. The signal of each line
                            returns through a common ground.</gloss></item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <!--Image at the end of the advertising section, it's a facsimile-->
            <div xml:id="fac_img9">
                <head facs="#imtArea_0">GOLDEN</head>
                <p facs="#imtArea_1"><address><street>1265 Broadway at 32nd St. </street><postCode>New York, 10001</postCode></address></p>
                <p facs="#imtArea_2">For Orders Call</p>
                <p facs="#imtArea_3"><num>800&#8226;221&#8226;3160</num></p>
                <p facs="#imtArea_4">For Information Call <num>212 &#8226; 725 &#8226; 1234</num></p>
                <p facs="#imtArea_5">
                    <lb/>OPEN 7 DAYS: 8AM-8PM FOR PHONE ORDERS
                    <lb/>VISA. MasterCard Welcome &#8226; Minimum Order <measure type="currency">$50</measure>
                    <lb/><measure type="currency">$2.50</measure> Service Charge For Orders Under <measure type="currency">$50</measure>
                    <lb/>Minimum Shipping <measure type="currency">$4.95</measure> &#8226; Over <measure quantity="3">3 Ibs.</measure> Add <measure type="currency">$ 50</measure> per lb
                    <lb/>Not responsible for Typo Errors or Manufacturers Price Changes
                    <lb/>Quantities Limited
                </p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
    <facsimile>
        <surface>
            <graphic xml:id="IM9" url="./img/fig9.png" width="682px" height="528px"></graphic>
            <zone xml:id="imtArea_0" ulx="10" uly="12" lrx="672" lry="174" rend="visible"></zone>
            <zone xml:id="imtArea_1" ulx="20" uly="180" lrx="652" lry="225" rend="visible"></zone>
            <zone xml:id="imtArea_2" ulx="203" uly="224" lrx="465" lry="261" rend="visible"></zone>
            <zone xml:id="imtArea_3" ulx="10" uly="272" lrx="675" lry="334" rend="visible"></zone>
            <zone xml:id="imtArea_4" ulx="14" uly="335" lrx="665" lry="375" rend="visible"></zone>
            <zone xml:id="imtArea_5" ulx="64" uly="380" lrx="615" lry="523" rend="visible"></zone>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
</TEI>
